Today's דף daf *daf* is ט"ט *tet-nine*, we pick up with the
משנה Mishnah *mishna* on the bottom of ח' עמוד ב' *chet-amud-bet*. For
those who were here yesterday, we dealt with a very challenging משנה
Mishnah *mishna*, which was all about a woman who's a נידה *nida*
or whatever, doesn't know what her status is and how to get
her sort of back on track, which is actually the classic, the
phrase of the משנה Mishnah *mishna* was, yeah, פתח *petach*, whether פתח
בתוך פתחי נידה *petach betoch pitchai nida*.
And as I pointed out there, there's a משנה *mishna* at the
end of third פרק *perek* of פרקי אבות *Pirkei Avot* that says,
קינים ופתחי נידה הן הן גופי הלכות *kinim upitchai nida hen hen
gufei halachot*. Those are two areas that require a lot of sort
of math as it were, קינים *kinim* and פתחי נידה *pitchai nida*.
קינים *kinim* is a whole מסכת *masechet* about birds and getting mixed
up and permutations. That those are real הלכות *halachot*, and they're very
challenging, and תקופות וגימטריאות פרפראות לחכמה *tkufot ugmatriot parparot lachochma*.
That questions about, yeah, the astronomical seasons and גימטריאות *gmatriot*, those are
more like spices, those are not as essential. Anyway, I mention it
because A, it mentions our משנה *mishna* from yesterday and points out
implicitly how difficult it is, but also the second part, תקופות *tkufot*,
is a little bit touches on the משנה *mishna* we're about to
do today. And this is another challenging סוגיא *sugya* here about the
question relating to ראש חודש chodesh, *Rosh Chodesh* and how many months
you're allowed to have in a year that are מלא malei, *malei*
or חסר chaser *chaseir*, that are full or they're lacking. So let's
take a look at the משנה *mishna*. אין פוחתין מארבעה חודשים המעוברים
בשנה *ein pochin me'arba'a chodashim hame'ubarim bashana*.
You have no fewer than four literally pregnant months, full months in
the year. Now this is a lunar calendar, we will, we're not
really going to discuss the solar correction, it'll come up a little
in the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*, but the focus is going to be
on the lunar aspect. So as people I assume know, a lunar
month is approximately 29 and a half days, a little bit more,
I'll point you out in a minute to the רש"י Rashi *Rashi*
that tells you how much more, but anyway, it's 29 and a
half days. So if it's 29 and a half days, how do
you, and you're on a lunar calendar, how long are your months
going to be? So they will alternate between 29 and 30. And
that's why in a standard Hebrew year, there's six months of 29,
six that are חסר chaser *chaseir*, and six that are מלא malei
*malei*, full or מעובר me'ubar. *me'ubar*. Now, you are allowed a certain
amount of variation. Why you might have to do variation, well one
obvious reason is that if you're basing it on the testimony of
witnesses and the witnesses don't come on a particular day, and it
was supposed to be 29, it was made 30, and you're going
to have to correct that maybe at a later time, although that's
also a challenge because then the not, it doesn't, that also depends
on when the witnesses come. But anyway, one thing is, one thing
is that correction, but sometimes you get a little off. So anyway,
how much variation are you allowed? So it says, you cannot go
fewer than four months that are אין פוחתין מארבעה חודשים המעוברים *ein
pochin me'arba'a chodashim hame'ubarim*, that are full, which is basically a variation
of two. You should have six and six. You're allowed to vary
two. You're allowed to go as few as four full months. ולא
נראה יתר על שמונה *velo nireh yeter al shmona*. And this is
a strange phrase, the גמרא Gemara. *Gemara* says it means לא נראה
לחכמים *lo nireh lachachamim*, it did not appear appropriate to do more
than eight, which sounds like at least for now the way we'll
read it, it's the variation on the other side. So it can
be six, no fewer than four, no more than eight. You're allowed
to have a variation from the what it should be, the six,
two on either side. Okay, and that is going to be the
entire focus of the גמרא Gemara. *Gemara*. The rest of the משנה
*mishna* is basically ignored by the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*, but let's read
it. שתי הלחם אין נאכלות פחות משניים ולא יתר על שלושה *shtei
halechem ein ne'echalot pachot mishnayim velo yeter al shlosha*. The שתי הלחם
*shtei halechem*, the two loaves that you would have for שבועות Shavuot
*Shavuot*, cannot be eat, will not be eaten in fewer than on
the second day of it being baked, and not more than the
third day. Again, this is for those who were not here yesterday,
just a series, a little survey through ש"ס *Shas* with the theme
of no fewer than this and no more than that. And that's
a collection of משניות *mishnayot* around that theme. We started with ערכין
*Erchin*, but now we're just going through many, many different cases. So,
שבועות Shavuot, *Shavuot*, you do not bake the שתי הלחם *shtei halechem*
for שבועות Shavuot *Shavuot* on שבועות Shavuot. *Shavuot*. Therefore, חז"ל *Chazal* understand
that even though you bring it on שבועות Shavuot. *Shavuot* and it's
יום טוב Yom Tov *Yom Tov*, you don't, the baking of it
does not override שבועות Shavuot. *Shavuot*. So therefore on a normal שבועות
Shavuot *Shavuot*, it is baked ערב שבועות Shavuot, *erev Shavuot*, brought on
שבועות *Shavuot*, so brought on day two. If ערב שבועות *erev Shavuot*
is שבת Shabbat. *Shabbat*, it is baked ערב שבת Erev Shabbat, *erev
Shabbat* and brought on שבועות *Shavuot*, so therefore on day three. That
is the שתי הלחם *shtei halechem*. לחם הפנים *lechem hapanim*, the bread,
the showbread, the bread on the שולחן *shulchan* in the, in the
בית המקדש Beit HaMikdash, *Beit Hamikdash*, אין נאכל פחות מתשעה ולא יתר
על אחד עשר *ein ne'echal pachot mitisha velo yeter al achad asar*.
Is not eaten in fewer than nine days from the days of
it being baked and not more than 11. Why? Again, you do
not bake it on שבת Shabbat *Shabbat*. Also though, you only eat
it a week after, the שבת Shabbat *Shabbat* after it's placed on
the table. So in an average case, it is baked on Friday,
day one. It is put on the, on the שולחן *shulchan* on
שבת Shabbat. *Shabbat*, day two. It is eaten next שבת Shabbos. *Shabbat*,
just add seven, day nine. So in an average case, it is
eaten... on day nine of from the day it is baked, counting
the day it is baked itself as day one. How can it
be as much as 11? If the two days before שבת Shabbos
are two days of ראש השנה Rosh Hashanah where they would actually
have two days of יום טוב Yom Tov even in ארץ ישראל,
Eretz Yisrael, so add two days and you get 11 because it
would not be baked on יום טוב Yom Tov, either, which is
interesting because you do do you can do מלאכה melacha for cooking
on יום טוב, Yom Tov, but you're not going to eat it
on יום טוב, Yom Tov, you're going to eat it nine days
later, so you don't bake it on יום טוב, Yom Tov. you
bake it on ערב יום טוב. Erev Yom Tov. Okay. Now,
a קטן katan is not given a ברית מילה brit milah fewer
than eight days, obviously eight days is the day of the מילה.
milah. By the way, here again we are counting the day of
born as day number one, not eight days after, right? It's confusing
a little, but anyway you count that as day one, so the
same day of the week a week later is day eight. And
not more than 12. Now what does it mean not more than
12? I mean if somebody never got a ברית מילה brit milah
they get a ברית מילה brit milah as an adult, and if
some baby was jaundiced or whatever, right, you also, but it means
assuming a healthy baby and the only you there's still possible that
you would have to wait till day 12. Why? One minute, because
let's say the baby is born on Friday, בין השמשות bein hashmashot
Friday and שבת. Shabbos When do you do the ברית מילה? brit
milah? You cannot do the ברית מילה brit milah on Friday because
maybe he was born on שבת Shabbat, and then it's a day
early. You cannot do it on שבת Shabbat, because maybe he was
born on Friday and then it's not eighth day and a non-eighth
day does not override שבת. Shabbat So therefore you do it on
Sunday. So in that scenario, now which day are we going to
count as one? So we're going to call Friday one because it's,
you know, it was בין השמשות bein hashmashot Friday שבת. Shabbos, So
Friday is one, שבת Shabbos, is two, the next שבת Shabbos, is
nine, and and therefore
the what do you call it, נו, nu, the
the Sunday is 10. So in that case ערב שבת, Friday, שבת,
counting Friday as one, his ברית מילה brit milah would be 10.
How do you get to 12? Well, again, let's assume that it
was that when you get to the next שבת, the Sunday, Monday
following, you were going to do it Sunday was two days יום
טוב. So you can't do it then either, so now 10 becomes
12. Okay, so that's how you get between eight and 12. Charlie.
I don't think this משנה of the פנים panim bread is correct
because if Thursday is ראש השנה, Rosh Hashanah, that would mean the
following שבת will be יום כיפור, Yom Kippur, you wouldn't be able
to eat it until the next day.
Hmm, that is a great question.
Unless it and for eating the פנים panim bread over on יום
כיפור? Yom Kippur?
No, no, no, no, that is a great question. What I would
say though is that while for us,
great question, but while for us two days ראש השנה Rosh Hashanah
the first day is one תשרי, Tishrei, when they had two days
ראש השנה Rosh Hashanah in the בית המקדש, Beit HaMikdash Tuesday actually
day one day one was the reason they had two days was
because day one was the second day ראש השנה. Rosh Hashanah. But
it was a great question.
But in the בית המקדש two days ראש השנה Rosh Hashanah means
the second day is is one תשרי, Tishrei, not the first. But
that close, that close to like a perfect question.
The first day would be the 30th of אלול, Elul, which they
which they never had for for ראש השנה. Rosh Hashanah.
All right, but anyway, but in that hypothetical scenario. Now we are
going to look at the at the גמרא Gemara with the entire
focus being on this issue of the עיבור ibbur months of the
year, of how many of is it six as an average of
medium of 30-day months, but it can vary anywhere between four to
eight. We allow that amount of variation. So let's take a look
in the גמרא. Gemara Before we do that, let's just I would
just want to point out to you one רש"י Rashi. that tells
you how many
you know what, let's one minute, no, let's not read that רש"י.
Rashi Okay, so let's take a look at the גמרא. Gemara So
the גמרא Gemara says, מאי לאו, mai lav, מאי לא נראה יתר
על שמונה? mai lo nira yeter al shmonah? What does it mean?
Because I read it that there's not more than eight full months,
but the גמרא Gemara says that's a little ambiguous phrase. So אמר
רב הונא לא נראה לחכמים לעבר יתר על שמונה. Amar Rav Huna
lo nira lachachamim le'aber yeter al shmonah. So that's what we said,
no fewer than four, no more than eight full months. מאי שנא
תשעה דלא? mai shna tisha delo? Why not nine? דאם כן קדים
אתי סיהרא תלתא יומי. de'im ken kadim asi sira tlata yomei. Because
then you'll see the new moon three days before ראש השנה. Rosh
Hashanah. Now you actually don't need any math to figure that out,
right? Because it's really I mean, you know, there's huge דרשות Drashas
here and you see tiny print תוספות Tosfos and he works it
all through for you, but I'm going to do the very simple
bottom line version of this. Okay, if the average is six, if
to have 29 and a half day lunar calendars you have months
you have six 29-day, six 30-day, so if you're off, so if
you have three extra
full-day months, then that means you're pushing off the coming ראש השנה
Rosh Hashanah three days from when it should be, which means the
new month, the new moon appears three days before ראש השנה. Rosh
Hashanah. Very simple. Got it? Yes? Okay. So קדים אתי סיהרא תלתא
יומי. kadim asi sira tlata yomei. So you'll see the new moon
three days before ראש השנה. Rosh Hashanah. So that obviously and that'll
make a mockery of it, right? You know, people making making ראש
השנה Rosh Hashanah three days after they saw the new moon. So
we can't allow for that amount of variation. So the גמרא Gemara
says השתא נמי. hashta nami. So okay, what are you going to
say? Only two days? So קדימתי תרי יומי. kadimati terei yomei. So
you'll see the new moon two days before ראש השנה. Rosh Hashana.
So here's the גמרא's Gemara answer, כי אמר רב משרשיא, ki amar
Rav Mesharshiya, like רב משרשיא Rav Mesharshiya says, כגון שהיתה שנה מעוברת.
kegon shehayeta shana meuberet. He says in another context which we're going
to get to in a minute, that we're talking about a שנה
מעוברת, shana meuberet, a leap year. So you could have a חודש
מעוברת, chodesh meuberet,
a full month, which is 30 days, you could have a שנה
מעוברת, shana meuberet, which is an extra month in the year. And
therefore,
הכא נמי כגון שהיתה שנה מעוברת, hacha nami kegon shehayeta shana meuberet,
הכא נמי כגון שהיתה שנה שלפניה מעוברת. hacha nami kegon shehayeta shana
shelifaneha meuberet. The previous year was a leap year. Now, why it
has to be the previous, רש"י Rashi discusses, I don't want to
get into it, it doesn't really matter previous or this year was
a leap year. What happens if you add an extra month? It
depends how many days that extra month is going to be, because
if you're making a leap year, again, the question is not being
off the month from when the moon appears. So if you're going
to add one more month, it's going to either have to be
29 days or 30 days. But actually, if you're adding another lunar
cycle, it's 29 and a half days. So right, do you understand?
Because how it's going to affect how you sync the new month
with when the moon appears. So by adding a new month, you're
going to get your calendar off either a half day in either
direction, right? If you make the month 29 days, then the months
are going to be a half day out of sync, right, the
next new month and so on. If you make it 30 days,
it's going to be a half day out of sync in the
other way. Is that clear or not so much? Yes? Okay. So
now it says like that, so בעיבור שנה חודש, be'ibur shana chodesh,
and your new month, you made a חודש, chodesh, which means a
29-day month. So because you made it a 29-day month,
therefore, דל ירחא מליא והדר ירחא חסירא, dal yarcha malye vehadar yarcha
chaseira,
so
you remove a full month to correspond to the lacking month that
you've just added. ואתא, ve'ata, and therefore it's not so bad. What
does this mean? It means the following, let me see if I
can explain in words if not I'll draw on the board. It
means like this, again,
your calendar was perfect.
You had six full, six lacking, which exactly corresponded to a 29
and a half day cycle. But when you have 13 months in
the year and you add a month, you're going to be a
little bit off, right, because it's not going to average 29 and
a half. So if you add that extra month as a 29-day
month, so then when you get let's say to the ראש השנה,
Rosh Hashana, let's say it was otherwise six and six and you
got to the ראש השנה, Rosh Hashana, right, the month would actually,
the new moon would actually appear half a day after ראש השנה,
Rosh Hashana, because you only had 29 days, but actually the extra
month was 29 and a half days. So it actually appeared half
a month after, half a day after. So therefore, if you make
two extra, two 30 extra 30-day months and you push ראש השנה
Rosh Hashana off two days, actually ראש השנה Rosh Hashana is actually
only going to be a day and a half now after the
new moon. It's not going to really be a full two days,
it'll only be a day and a half. So a day and
a half is an error which we can tolerate. It doesn't look
so terrible to people that it's ראש השנה Rosh Hashana and the
new moon was a day and a half earlier. Okay, so, but
the גמרא Gemara now asks that question. The גמרא Gemara says וכדי
כדי יומא, vechadi chadi yoma, you're still a day off. רש"י Rashi
says a day doesn't literally mean a day, a day and a
half. Okay, but you're still not perfect, fine. So you said because
it was 29 and it wasn't 29 and a half, it's not
exactly two days, it's a day and a half, a day, but
you're still off. So the גמרא Gemara says, okay,
לא אדעתיה דאינשי. lo adatei de'inshei. All right, people aren't paying so
close attention, a day, a day and a half. You know, but
three days, that's going to be big. Okay, and even the גמרא
Gemara assumes two days would be big, but already within a day
and a half, it wouldn't be so blatant to people that ראש
השנה Rosh Hashana is off.
Just instead of worrying it being a day and a half off,
just do, you know, beforehand, make a couple 29, a more 29.
No, no, no, no, because then you don't have, then the whole
point is we allow you to have more, obviously you can always
manipulate and have half and half. We're saying that if we, how
much will we allow you to be off from half and half?
So you can't say, oh, the answer is if you have too
many full months, make more half months. Then you're saying don't have
half and half, then you're saying have half and half, and we're
saying we're allowing you to have up to, you know.
But let's say you did, and
don't come late.
No, let's say you said you have six. So if you know
it's going to need to be a leap year, then you said
you can have anywhere from.
You can never correct for the leap year to get you exactly
precise, because by adding a month, you're adding a 29 and a
half day cycle and you can only represent it by 29 days
or 30 days. There's no way you can correct for a half
day off until you get to your next leap year. There's no
way you can have a half.
But the year before, you can do like a couple of, you
know. Yeah, right?
No, because that makes an entire shift of a day, not of
a half day. The only time you're going to be able to
correct perfectly for a half day is the next leap year, because
you're going from an even number to an odd number.
No, meaning the year before, I understand, instead of a day and
a half, you'd be off by a half a day or whatever
it is or a day, which would still be a better margin
of.
Okay, but we're not talking with that degree of advanced planning.
Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says like this. עולא אמר Ulla Amar
so עולא Ulla says, so that's fine, so you have a range
between
it should be six, you have a range between four and eight
because that amount of being off we can tolerate but not more
than that. עולא אמר לא נראה לחכמים לחסר יתר משמונה. Ulla Amar
lo nira lachachamim lechaser yeter mishmona. What that actually means is not
that so which is which is you can't have fewer than it's
really saying the same thing in different words. You cannot have fewer
than four full months because
you cannot have more than eight lacking months. It's
the other half of the picture. You can't have fewer than four
full months because if you had fewer than four full months you'd
have if you had three full months you'd have nine lacking months.
So why can't you have fewer than four full months? Because you
can't have more than eight lacking months. So it's not really adding
any new information. Okay, so he's going to talk about ומאי טעמא
קאמר umai taama kaamar and it's explaining the reason.
מה טעם אין פוחתין מארבעה חדשים המעוברין בשנה? ma taam ein pochtin
mearbaa chadashim hameubarim bashana? משום דלא נראה לחכמים לחסר יתר משמונה mishum
delo nira lachachamim lechaser yeter mishmona because they don't want to have
more than eight lacking months. Why not? Because it's going to be
the problem about being off in the other direction. מאי
שנא תשעה דלא? mai shna tisha delo? Why do you not want
nine lacking months? דאם כן ליהוי סיהרא תלתא יומי deim ken lihavei
saira tlata yomei because then the moon will be three days after
ראש השנה, Rosh Hashanah, right? The problem before was was that if
you're going to have too many I'm sorry, no no, it's the
same problem. No, no, I'm sorry, right, it's the opposite. The problem
before was was that if you had too many full months you'd
push ראש השנה Rosh Hashanah three days if you had nine full
months you'd push ראש השנה Rosh Hashanah three days after the new
moon. Well, the reverse is true if you have nine lacking months,
right? Six gets you precise. If you have nine lacking months, the
previous year is shorter, so ראש השנה Rosh Hashanah occurs three days
before the new moon. So we don't want to allow that. Okay,
so it's just explaining why we can't be too much off, can't
have too many lacking months. So the גמרא Gemara says דנו? denu?
So why is eight okay? השתא נמי קא מיחסר תרי יומי. hashta
nami ka michaser trei yomei. Here too you have two days where
two extra days meaning the moon appears two days after ראש השנה.
Rosh Hashanah. So כדאמר רב משארשיא. kedamar Rav Mesharshiya. Oh, so here's
like רב משארשיא Rav Mesharshiya said כגון דהויא שנה מעוברת. kegon dehavya
shana meuberet. Same idea, except whenever you have a leap year it
allows you you can be off a half a day either direction.
Putting in a leap year is going to force you to make
29 or 30 on a month that's really 29 and a half,
so it's going to set you off a half a day. So
rather than before what we said a leap year with and you
made your month 29 which actually which actually shaved a half which
actually pushed you forward a half I'm getting confused. When we said
before you made it 29 instead of 29 and a half it
pulled you back a half a day. So here we're going to
say
no, is that right? When it was supposed to be 29 and
a half and you made it 29, right, then then it put
the
then
how'd it work? Now I confused myself. One minute, so there when
it was supposed to be there the problem was the first okay,
the first case was was you had too many עיבור ibur years
too many too many full months and ראש השנה Rosh Hashanah was
too much ahead. And right, and it was corrected because if you
only had a 29 day month then it pulled you back a
half of a day. Correct. So here it's going to be the
opposite. You have a 30 day month, it's going to push you
forward a half a day. כגון דהויא שנה מעוברת kegon dehavya shana
meuberet הכא נמי כגון דהויא שנה שלפניה מעוברת hacha nami kegon dehavya
shana shelifneha meuberet דל ירחא חסירא בהדי ירחא מליא dal yarcha chasira
behadi yarcha malya so we can subtract a lacking month opposite the
full month and therefore we are do not are three days we
are not two days off we're only one day off. So again,
what's the case? We're describing a scenario where you have eight lacking
months. So if you have eight lacking months, ראש השנה Rosh Hashanah
now appeared two days before the new moon, but you had a
leap year, so you had another 29 and a half days, but
you represented that by a 30 day month. If so you basically
inserted an extra half a day beyond what the exact cycle was.
So so that actually pushed you forward. So instead of having ראש
השנה Rosh Hashanah
two days after the new year two days after the מולד, molad,
you only had it a day and a half after the מולד.
molad.
Okay, is this more or less clear to people? Yes? Have I
managed to confuse everybody? Okay, what?
It is. Okay, good. All right, so okay, so all right, good.
So anyway, so the so the problem was you had too many
too many lacking months. ראש השנה Rosh Hashanah was too far ahead,
but because you had a 30 day month instead of a for
a 29 and a half day cycle, it was only instead of
two days ahead only a day and a half ahead. Okay, so
the גמרא Gemara says like this. השתא נמי קא מיחסר תרי hashta
nami ka michaser trei I'm sorry, the גמרא Gemara says דנו denu
ואכתי איכא חד יומא. veachti ika chad yoma. So
what? But you're still off. day ahead, so the גמרא Gemara. says,
and you know, the new moon appears a day after ראש השנה,
Rosh Hashana, so the גמרא Gemara says סברי איתחזי איתחזי איתחזייא ואנן
לאו אדעתין. Savri itchazi itchazi itchazyei ve'anan lav adatin.
So here there's actually a better way people can tolerate if you're
off. In this scenario, ראש השנה Rosh Hashana occurred before the new
moon. So when it's ראש השנה, Rosh Hashana, you look up in
the sky. Now what do you see a day before the new
moon? You don't see the old moon. In that middle day, you
see nothing. So there, there, that we can tolerate because there you
have ראש השנה, Rosh Hashana, you haven't yet seen the new moon,
you think, oh, maybe in ירושלים Yerushalayim they've seen it, maybe it
was cloudy. So therefore, they're able to tolerate that and accept if
you're only a day, a day and a half off. More than
that though, they're already, right, seeing, more than that though, they're probably
already seeing last month's old moon while it's ראש השנה Rosh Hashana
and that would of course be unacceptable. But once you're already in
that bit with just one day off, one day early, that can
be tolerated. So that's why the גמרא Gemara, says why do we
allow for two? Because two in a leap year translates into, in
a certain type of a leap year, translates into one and a
half and that can be
tolerated.
Yes. But if they see a crescent moon that's an old moon,
it's going to be at a different time of the day with,
I mean there's all...
That's why you can't tolerate that. That's exactly my point. You can't,
if they were more than a day and a half off, if
ראש השנה Rosh Hashana then you would be seeing last month's moon
and that would obviously be last month. But if you see nothing,
you see nothing, so maybe it was seen in ירושלים, Yerushalayim, what
do you know? Okay, so that is actually better than the other
answer which was לאו אדעתא דאינשי lav adatta de'inshei because the other
case was you've already been seeing the new moon for a day
and then you have ראש השנה Rosh Hashana a day later. Right,
so that's a little harder to, people don't pay so close attention.
If it's ראש השנה, Rosh Hashana, they're looking up in the sky.
If it's not ראש השנה, Rosh Hashana, who's looking?
Two days ראש השנה. Rosh Hashana. You know, one is, weren't they
always doing ספק safek anyway, in which case they're kind of planning,
so you know, I would think that somehow that should fall in...
Well, it's not exactly clear. We're assuming that they're still doing it
based on witnesses, that they haven't fixed the calendar.
But בשלמא ספק bishlama safek when they're doing it anyway, so maybe
witnesses would come. Right.
Oh, about the two days ראש השנה? Rosh Hashana? Yeah. Um,
yeah, but you know, if you don't want to say that it's
obvious you're off by ראש השנה, Rosh Hashana, you could say it's
obvious you're off by סוכות. Succos. I mean, it's like, you know,
it's...
You're right, it's an interesting question. Why didn't the גמרא Gemara, use
to explain how more mistake could be tolerated based on the idea
of two days ראש השנה? Rosh Hashana? Um, but that would have
only helped for one of the directions, not the other one. I'd
have to figure it out. But anyway, it's only going to, right,
it's not going to help both ways, it's going to only help
one way.
But the other thing you're saying is you're assuming a lack of
planning, but like, you know, they knew that every so often they
had to have a leap year. So the month before, you're saying,
oh, they fixed it, it would be a problem. So the month
before, the year before, do like four and...
But they didn't know that this year they were going to... If
they were doing extra months for, to correct, to get the calendar
back in sync, then you wouldn't have these limits. The only reason
for these limits is that for some reason, and it's not even
explaining what the reason is, בית דין, Beis Din, you know,
what's it, meeting that day and some accident happened, who knows? Okay,
but if you're correcting the calendar and getting it back in sync,
you do as many leap years or as many חסר chaser, months
as, I mean leap months or חסר chaser, months as you need.
Here's a case where it should be six and six and you're
actually deviating from the norm. So it doesn't explain what those situations
would be that would lead to that. Okay, we're actually going to
see a case at the end of today's דף where they had
nine as opposed to eight, but they had it because they needed
to correct and then that was fine. Okay, so let's, okay, so
basically that was a little confusing. I think I made it, you
know, sort of, I cut out most of the math and I
think it's really clear. All you realize is that the average is
six, so eight and four are two off and that's the two
off. And then the aspect that I said of when you have
to have a leap month, you're going to obviously have a half
day off because a 29 and a half days has to be
represented by one month by 29 or 30. So that's basically the
point. Two days we tolerate because in a case of a leap
year it translates into a day and a half. Three days we
don't tolerate.
Just to make sure I understand, so you're saying this is like,
you know, when you're going to correct it, you'll do like the
four and the nine. But like let's say the year, let's say
whatever it was, for some reason, the whole time, every time that
they came on like day 30, day 30, day 30, the whole
time because... then the בית דין Beis Din would tolerate that, right?
Because that's what you have to do מקדש על פי הראייה. mekadesh
al pi hare'iyah.
So that is a good question, right? What does it mean you
don't allow, that's an excellent question. What does it mean you don't
allow more than this? Let's say we already have eight leap months
because the עדים edim are always asleep at the wheel and coming
in late. And now this month, this year as well they came
late. Can we do קידוש על פי, kiddush al pi, you know,
on our own without עדים? edim? And but you know, it's hard
to imagine that scenario because if we're already off by two months,
you know, then the עדים edim will have had three days to
come, the calendar's already way off. So they'll have had three days
to come from the last month and they're still coming four days
late rather than, you know, and so on. But I don't know,
I mean, but okay, you could say they could be, we could
look up in the sky ourselves and do our own קידוש החודש.
Kiddush HaChodesh. So you're right, I don't know what the answer is.
It's hard to imagine the scenario, but what happens if you find
yourself stuck? Do you basically do your own
קידוש? kiddush? The implication is that if you really want to keep
by these parameters, you're going to have to maybe ignore the presence
or absence of עדים eidim in order to do it. Okay, let's
take a look at the גמרא. Gemara
במאי קמיפלגי. B'mai kamifligi. Now what is this debate? Now it doesn't
really seem like a debate either way we said, a variation between
between four and eight, but you'll realize that the last position only
said you can go down to four עיבור ibur months, but it
did not say you can go up to eight, which is the
logical alternative point, the flip side of the coin. Go down to
four, you can go up to eight. But the other one said
no, no, no, the משנה is only saying you can go down
to four. It's not saying you can go up to eight.
Wait, so she can go up to more or less?
No, but you can't go beyond six. Your whole variation is four
and six. Why if you're allowed to drop down to four, why
can't you go up to eight? So let's take a look, במאי
קמיפלגי, b'mai kamifligi, what's the debate? בעיבור שנה, B'ibur shana, with this
exact question of when you make an extra month in the year,
what what size can it be? Okay, let's take a look, דתניא,
detanya, taught in a ברייתא. Baraisa. כמה עיבור שנה? Kama ibur shana?
What is the month that you add to a year? ל', Lamed,
30 days. רבן שמעון בן גמליאל Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel אומר omer
חודש, it can be a month. Now a month means what does
that mean? It means either 29 or 30. Okay, so if you
remember, the way we were able to explain, actually it's not six,
it's seven. The way we were able to explain why we tolerate
going up having as many as eight is because as eight full
months is because in a case of an עיבור ibur year, eight
actually becomes seven and seven is not so bad. When? When it
becomes seven? Mean when you add the extra month and you're only
adding a 29-day month for a 29 and a half day cycle,
then it becomes then being off by two days becomes being off
by a day and a half. But that assumes that you can
add a 29-day month for an for an עיבור ibur year. But
if you're not but that's one of the opinions here. But if
you can only add a 30-day month for an עיבור ibur year,
you're never going to be able to get those two days off
to cut it back to a day and a half off. So
therefore if you say you don't have the answer of עיבור ibur
year to pull it back if you only allow adding a 30-day
month. So therefore if you're of the position you can only add
a 30-day month, the most I can tolerate is not eight but
seven. Because eight will never become seven and a half. Okay, so
therefore that's why he doesn't read the משנה that way, and according
to him, you're allowed to go between four and seven. Four because
based on an עיבור ibur year, that extra those two days that
four can essentially be a five, meaning it pulls it back a
half a day, and seven can become a six and a half,
but we won't allow eight because I'm not seven will be seven.
We won't allow eight because eight will never be able to be
pulled back. Okay, so what was the rationale
to make it always 30 days? Yeah, so that's not discussed.
Yeah, I don't know.
I'd have to see, it comes up it's in a תוספתא, Tosefta,
so I don't even
know. It's a good question, I really don't know.
It could just be an assumption that a standard month, you know,
it's funny, what's the standard? They call a 29-day month חסר, chaser.
and they call a 30-day month, you know, מעובר. So what is
considered to be the standard?
But I think that the assumption is that a standard is 30.
So the idea you add a month, you add a standard-sized month.
But I don't know if there's something more to it than that.
Why not make it a 28-day month? That would make sense.
Yeah, I know. I understand. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says like
this. Okay, מיתיבי. Meisivei. I'll ask you on this on this idea
that, you know, about about how much can you vary, is it
between four and eight or only between four and seven in terms
of in terms of the 30-day months? So now we get into
interesting stuff about how it relates even to how our calendar is
structured today. אין עצרת חלה, Ein Atzeret chala, שבועות does not occur,
אלא ביום הנף, ela b'yom hanaf, only on the day of the
waving of the עומר. Omer. Now that's an obvious point, right? Because
when you bring
the עומר, Omer, you start counting ספירת העומר. Sefirat HaOmer. ספירת העומר
Sefirat HaOmer is seven weeks. Okay, so when does ספירת העומר Sefirat
HaOmer end? On if you start counting עומר Omer on Sunday, ספירת
העומר Sefirat HaOmer is going to end on שבת, right? Because the
end of seven weeks, the end of one week will be שבת,
seven weeks will be שבת, and the next day is שבועות, which
is the same day you started. So the day you start counting
ספירת העומר, Sefirat HaOmer, if you just think, right, if that was
day one in the calendar, 8, 15, 22, whatever, you're going to
get to day 50, right? If you keep on adding seven to
one. So it's going to be שבועות will always be the second
day of פסח, Pesach, the day you start counting the ספירה. Sefirah.
That will be שבועות. And
so that was obvious. ואין ראש השנה חלה, V'ein Rosh Hashanah chala,
אלא או ביום הנף או לאור עיבורו. ela o b'yom hanaf o
l'or iburo. ראש השנה Rosh Hashanah only occurs either on the day
of waving or on or עיבורו, iburo, the the day of the
pregnant part of the month. What does that mean? Here. Just to
do a quick demonstration. So here is, you know, פסח. Pesach. Here
is the day הנף hanaf is the waving of the עומר, omer,
so that's יום הנף, yom hanaf, the day you start counting ספירה.
Sefirah. Okay, so, so now you go down, right, you have 23,
30. So this 30 is considered עיבורו, iburo, okay, because it is
the 30th day of the month. Or עיבורו, iburo, sometimes אור or
means the night before, but anyway here it means, here it means
the next day, day 31. So basically what we're saying is ראש
השנה Rosh Hashanah will either fall, it's an easy way to say
it, is יום הנף yom hanaf or on, we're talking about the
day of the week, right? So it's the same day of a
week of this or the day after. One of these two days
is going to be ראש השנה. Rosh Hashanah. Now, why is, תוספות
Tosafot basically says that in one sentence. If you look at תוספות,
Tosafot, תוספות Tosafot says, where is,
שני חצאים ליומיא ט״ז בניסן... shnei chatza'im l'yomaya tet zayin b'Nissan...
well whatever, I'm not going to read the תוספות. Tosafot.
Okay, anyway, so this is ראש השנה. Rosh Hashanah. Why is it
one of those days ראש השנה? Rosh Hashanah? Because think, think about
it the following way. Okay, if this is day 15, what was
the first day of ניסן? Nissan? Same day, right? So it's also
day one of ניסן. Nissan. Day one of ניסן Nissan is, is
this. Now, between ניסן Nissan and ראש השנה Rosh Hashanah are six
months, okay? Six months, one is מלא, malei, one is חסר, chaser
which means that, here's the, here's the trick. How of, if you
want to figure out day of the week, it's how off is
any month, given month, from a perfect number of weeks? A day
and a half on the average, right? If it's 29 or, and,
it's 29 or 30. Right, it's a day and a half on
the average, which is fine if you have an equal number of
מלא malei and חסר. chaser. So six times a day and a
half is, anybody? Nine. So that means take out another seven for
a perfect week and you're two days off. So ראש השנה Rosh
Hashanah is two days off from the day of פסח. Pesach. Okay,
full number of weeks plus if it's six months and it's an
average 29 and a half, plus two days. So this is going
to be in a standard year of six, of, of equal number
of חסר chaser. and מלא, malei and we're going to talk about
how you could get it a day earlier. But obviously the way
it'll be a day earlier is in the six months between פסח
Pesach and ראש השנה, Rosh Hashanah, you had one month more that
was חסר. chaser You had a 29-day month instead of a 30-day
month and that'll pull it back a day. And in the current
calendar, it's always three and three. In the current calendar, it is
always three and three. What do you mean it's always three and
three? Three מלא malei. and three חסר. chaser Right, that's what I'm
saying, it's always perfect. Okay, now I'm going to show you another
trick, hold on, very important that רש״י Rashi actually quotes, and this
is a great trick and hopefully you won't forget this. If you
look at the little רש״י, Rashi, and that's not such a little
רש״י, Rashi, but I'll just read you, it's actually in the middle
of a רש״י. Rashi. If you go about 15, I don't know,
12 lines
up before the lines get wide, you see the רש״י Rashi
that starts with, it looks like בית שמאי, Beit Shammai, ב ש
ג ר. bet shin gimel resh. You see that? Yeah. So anyway
רש״י Rashi says ויש לנו סימן קבוע א״ת ב״ש ג״ר. ve-yesh lanu
siman kavua at bash gar. What does that mean? So this is
a great trick, okay, you are not going to forget this, I
hope. א ב ג ד ה ו. alef bet gimel dalet hey
vav. ת ש ר ק צ פ. tav shin resh kuf tzadi
pei. Actually this one isn't in the גמרא, Gemara but I'm going
to tell you so you'll get it anyway. So this is the
day of פסח. Pesach. Okay, the first day of פסח Pesach is
the same day of the year that תשעה באב... Tisha B'Av... well
done. I'm not going to do the math for it. The second
day of פסח, Pesach, what did we just say? שבועות. Second day
of פסח Pesach is שבועות. Third day of פסח, Pesach, ראש השנה.
Rosh Hashanah. What we just said, ראש השנה. Rosh Hashanah. Amazing. Fourth
day of פסח Pesach is קריאת התורה, Kriat HaTorah, which means שמחת
תורה. Simchat Torah. Now you can, and now that's easy, you know
why? קריאת התורה, Kriat HaTorah, שמחת תורה. Simchat Torah. Now you know
why? Because if this day is ראש השנה, Rosh Hashanah, so then
the eighth day of פסח Pesach is the same, שמחת תורה Simchat
Torah is the ninth day of פסח... Pesach... eighth day of סוכות
Sukkot is the same as the first day of ראש השנה, Rosh
Hashanah, so שמחת תורה Simchat Torah is the ninth. Now ה hey
is צום, tzom, יום כיפור. Yom Kippur. Okay? Right? So that's how
you get, so this is ראש השנה, Rosh Hashanah, this is one,
so it's also eight, nine, ten. Yeah. Right? See that? Right? Wow.
If this is ראש השנה, Rosh Hashanah, it's also the same day
of סוכות, Sukkot, so plus one gets you שמחת תורה, Simchat Torah,
right? Same day of סוכות Sukkot is also eighth day of סוכות
Sukkot plus one, so that gets you שמחת תורה Simchat Torah and
this plus eight and then nine, ten gets you יום כיפור. Yom
Kippur. ו vav is פורים. Purim. I'm not going to figure that
one out for you, okay, but that's basically a little bit working
backwards, right? Because, you know, working backwards from the first day of...
because the first day of פסח Pesach is the first day of
ניסן, Nissan, and פורים Purim is like, you know, like two weeks
back, whatever, anyway you'll figure that out by yourself. And this is
not a part of it, but somebody figured out the 7th day...
what? יום העצמאות? Yom Ha'atzmaut? Yes! The 7th day of פסח Pesach
is יום העצמאות! Yom Ha'atzmaut! So there you go, you got that
all figured out. Is this explicitly from this רש״י? Rashi? No, well
רש״י Rashi says we have this tradition, I mean I don't know,
רש״י Rashi didn't invent it, I don't know what
the first recorded,
yeah, I don't know what the first basis of that is. Okay,
so getting back to the גמרא, Gemara one minute, so now the
גמרא Gemara says, okay, ואין ראש השנה חל אלא ביום הנף, Ve'ein
Rosh Hashanah chal ela beyom hanaf, so ראש השנה Rosh Hashanah will
fall out either on the same day as the second day of
פסח, Pesach, או לאור עיבורו, o le'or iburo, or the third day
of פסח. Pesach. So as we've shown on a perfect, you know,
on a six, on the three and three, an equal number of
מלאים וחסרים, maleim vechaserim, it's going to be the third day of
פסח. Pesach. So how are we going to get to one day
off and only one day off by coming moving backwards, right? You
would say if there's going to be variation, shouldn't it be variation
in either direction? Why don't we say that it'll either be on
the second day or the fourth day of פסח? Pesach? If on
a normal year it's the third day, why don't we speak about
a variation in both directions? That's going to be the question. So
let's take a look. The גמרא Gemara says like this: בשלמא לעולא,
Bishlama le'Ulla, it makes sense according to עולא, Ulla, דשמונה חסרים עבדינן,
Deshmoneh chaserim avdinan, מעוברים לא עבדינן, me'ubarin lo avdinan, that you can
have eight חסר chaser months, you can only really vary in terms
of your lacking months, you can't have actually more full months. So
therefore, now I understand it, because we're assuming that if you're going
to have eight חסר chaseir. months, you're going to distribute it equally
in the first half of the year and the second half of
the year. You could question that as well. Okay, but if we're
going to assume you're going to have two extra lacking months, one
will be before ניסן Nissan and the other will be after ניסן.
Nissan. So if you put in one lacking month after ניסן, Nissan,
you move it from the third day of פסח Pesach to the
second day of פסח. Pesach. Everybody with me? Yeah? Okay, so according
to him that you can have eight lacking months, we understand one
lacking month will occur in the second half of the year and
it'll pull and it'll pull ראש השנה Rosh Hashanah back a day.
So therefore, משכחת לה שניהם חסר ביום הנף, Meshachachat lah sheneihem chaser
beyom hanaf, if you have two lacking months, which which two does
it refer to? Maybe two months in a row that
are lacking, or you have both lacking months, one before פסח, Pesach,
one after. Anyway, if you have a lacking month after after ניסן,
Nissan, then you pulled
it back a
day and it's the second day of פסח. Pesach. אחד מלא ואחד
חסר, Echad malei ve'echad chaser, if it's your if it's your normal
year which alternates full and lacking, then לאור עיבורו, le'or iburo, the
third day of פסח, Pesach, okay? Normally the third day of פסח,
Pesach, if it's a year of two lacking months, which is one
in the first half, one in the second, then it gets pulled
back a day. Why can't it get pushed forward a day? Because
he only has extra lacking months, he doesn't have extra מלא malei
months. That makes sense. אלא לרב הונא, Ela leRav Huna, דאמר עבדינן
מעוברים, de'amar avdinan me'ubarin, but according to רב הונא Rav Huna that
says you can have up to eight full months, so so sometimes
you can have an extra full month in the second half of
the year. הזמנין דמשכחת לאור אור עיבורו, Hazimnin demeshachachat le'or or iburo,
it's the day after the day after the 30th day, okay? It's
not on the third day of פסח, Pesach, it's on the fourth
day of פסח. Pesach. We could also vary in the other direction.
So אמר לך רב הונא, Amar lach Rav Huna, רב הונא Rav
Huna would say to you, וליעולא מי ניחא? Ule'Ulla mi nicha? And
how does this anyway work according to עולא? Ulla? שמונה הוא דלא
עבדינן, Shmoneh hu dela avdinan, remember עולא Ulla said I'm not going
to go up to eight full months, הא שבעה עבדינן, ha shiva
avdinan, implicitly he would have allowed seven, because we do allow being
off by one day. He can't allow by being off by two
days because you don't have the correction of a half day and
so on. But implicitly even עולא Ulla would have agreed you could
have one extra full month. So if you could have one extra
full month, you have the same question. ראש השנה Rosh Hashanah can
fall out on the normal would be the third day, but it
could should be able to be the second or the fourth, because
you can have an extra at least one extra חסר chaseir or
one extra מלא. malei. הא שבעה עבדינן עבדינן שבעה. Ha shiva avdinan
avdinan shiva. Anyway, the extra שבעה shiva is extra. זימנין דלא עבדינן
בסיתווא, Zimnin dela avdinan besitva, so if you're going to have seven
full months, the one extra full month, sometimes we won't do it
in like the fall-winter period, we won't do it in the first
half of the year, ועבדינן בקייטא, ve'avdinan bekayta, we'll do it in
the spring-summer period. So since עולא Ulla allows for an extra full
month, maybe it should occur after פסח, Pesach, והוה לאור אור עיבורו,
vehavei le'or or iburo, that'll push off ראש השנה Rosh Hashanah a
day forward. So instead of being on the third day of פסח,
Pesach, it'll push it off to the fourth day of פסח. Pesach.
So okay, this is a problem. Why it says that ראש השנה
Rosh Hashanah can only be on the third or the second day
of פסח? Pesach? Because both not only according to me, but according
to everybody, it's possible to have an extra 30-day month and it
should be able to be also the fourth day of פסח. Pesach.
אלא, Ela, so how do we deal with it where it sets
such a limit for what ראש השנה Rosh Hashanah can be? הא
מני אחרים היא, Ha mani acherim hi, this is the position of
אחרים. Acherim. אחרים, Acheirim, normally assumed רבי מאיר, Rebbi Meir, דתניא, Detanya,
we taught in a ברייתא. Baraita. אחרים אומרים, Acheirim omrim, אחרים Acheirim
say, others say, says, אין בין עצרת לעצרת, Ein bein atzeret l'atzeret,
there is no more, there is not between one, one שבועות and
the next שבועות, ואין בין ראש השנה לראש השנה, V'ein bein Rosh
Hashanah l'Rosh Hashanah, and not between ראש השנה Rosh Hashanah and ראש
השנה, Rosh Hashanah, אלא ארבעה ימים בלבד, Ella arba'ah yamim bilvad, only
four days. Now this is also easy to figure out. Why? Because
again, remember, how many days off from a, is a, is a
normal lunar month from a, from an exact number of weeks? A
day and a half, right? Exact number of weeks 28, so on
the average, a, whatever, a day and a half. Especially if you
have a perfect year, right? Six and six, a day and a
half. So, how many, what day of the week, how much will
a calendar vary from one year to the, you know, from one
year to the next? Well, how many full weeks are there? So
first of all, just take out all of the perfect, you're left
with a day and a half. A day and a half times
12 is 18. Take out the full number of weeks, 14, what
do you left with? Four. Okay, there you go. So if you're
dealing with 29 and a half days, a perfect variation between 29
and 30, you're go, one year's calendar, the day of the week
it falls out and the next year's will be on the, off
four days from the day of the week. Clear? Wait, so how
did you, why did you take out the number of? Because if
it was an exact number of weeks, right, then it would fall
out on the same day. If the year was a precise number
of weeks, then every, every year, every ראש השנה Rosh Hashanah would
fall out on the same day. But
so you take out all the full weeks and you'll find out
that how much is a lunar year, divided by seven, what's the
remainder? The remainder of a lunar, I was just simplifying so you
didn't have to multiply 12 by 29 and a half. I multiplied
12 by one and a half. But the remainder of a lunar
year divided by seven is four. So the next year will be,
will be four days after, you know, the shift on the day
of the week will be four days. Okay, so now
the גמרא Gemara
says like this. There's, so there's four days between them. Now, ואם
הייתה שנה מעוברת, V'im hayta shanah m'uberet, if it was a leap
year, חמישה, Chamishah,
assuming that you add a 30 day, no, assuming that you add
I guess a
29 day month for
a leap year, right, because that would be, you put it off
only, that'll put it off only one day off, right, because as
opposed to 28, 29 is one more day shift. Okay, so therefore
since he has it fixed, that's why the ברייתא Baraita is going
according to him. Of course if he has it fixed, you've got
a problem, right? Because if he has it fixed, it should always
be day 31. And if you're saying, well maybe it was a
leap year, okay, right, but if it was a leap year, it
should be one day more forward, right, in terms of the day
of the week. So how is saying it goes like אחרים Acheirim
going to solve the problem and allow, I mean I don't mean
day 31, it's going to be whatever, yeah, the, I mean you
know, the third day of פסח. Pesach. How is that going to
explain why it can only be the second and third day? It's
very nice that he says his calendar is totally fixed, he's not
going to allow any variation off of the norm, he's going to
insist on six and six. Fine, that's all very nice, but then
it doesn't explain any fluctuation. And therefore why did we say third
or second day of פסח? Pesach? Yeah. And there's also no opinion
in the previous ברייתא Baraita that says the leap month is always
29 days. That's also true. That's a good point as well. So
this is a completely different opinion. So let's anyway take a look
what the גמרא Gemara. says like this. So the גמרא Gemara says,
although he says ואם הייתה שנה מעוברת חמישה, V'im hayta shanah m'uberet
chamishah, here's what the גמרא Gemara is going to say. סוף סוף
לאחרים ביום הנחלה משכחת לה, Sof sof l'Acheirim b'yom hanachlah meshakchat lah,
okay, then you'll get it on day three, but when are you
ever going to get it on day two? So אמר רב משארשיא,
Amar Rav Mesharshiya, ביום שהייתה שנה מעוברת, B'yom shehayta shanah m'uberet, it
was a leap year, ועיבור שנה ל' יום, V'ibur shanah lamed yom,
and it was 30 days. Now wait a minute, hold on, that
should be setting you off two days. One second, let me just
double check the רש"י here. Um, wait one minute. Oh, oh, okay,
ah, ah, here was the point. You have to correct, he's only
going to allow you to be off five for a leap year.
So what happens if you actually, right, the, where does the added
month come in a leap year? It comes back here, right, the
added month is in אדר, Adar, right? So the added month, it'll
make the relationship of this calendar to the previous one now off
by an extra day or two, but it's not going to affect
the distance between פסח Pesach and ראש השנה Rosh Hashanah because it
occurs before פסח. Pesach. So this added month was 30 days. But
according to him, he's not going to allow variation in more than
five days. He would have wanted it, to go to your question
משארשיא, Mesharshiya, he would have wanted this to be a 29 day
month, so it only would have pushed it off one extra day,
right, because he, right, if he only wants the variation from one
ראש השנה Rosh Hashanah to the next to be four, if you're
adding a month, he'll allow it to be five. But somebody wasn't
paying attention and made it 30 days. So now he insists that
the next ראש השנה Rosh Hashanah be no more than five days
from the previous one. So you've got two... to five, which is
the most variation he'll allow, you pull out a day, and that
brings it from the third day of פסח Pesach to the ראש
השנה Rosh Hashanah to the second day. Where do you pull out
the day from? Any of the next months you make one of
the 30 months you make it 29. You had two days here,
I mean you're setting it off from the day of the week
two extra days here, you would have only wanted it to be
one, so because he wants the calendar to be very
little variation, he's going
to insist that that's the key for him is the space between
the ראש השנה, Rosh Hashanahs, he's going to insist that you pull
out a day. I understand how you make anything, depends on the
witnesses. Well, that's the גמרא Gemara is going to say that. So
let's take a look at the גמרא. Gemara So the גמרא Gemara
says like this, כגון שהיתה שנה מעוברת עיבור שנה ל' יום. kegon
shehayta shana meuberet ibur shana lamed yom. So we actually made a
30-day month of an extra אדר. Adar. So now we're going to
be off by the next ראש השנה Rosh Hashanah is going to
be a six-day variation.
So דל ירחא לבהדי ירחא, dal yarcha l'vadei yarcha, so you have
to remove
a month for a month, meaning you make or subtract, meaning you
make an extra month a 29-day month, ומשתכח ליה יומא אנף, umishtachas
lei yoma anaf, and that pulls back ראש השנה Rosh Hashanah from
the third day of פסח Pesach to the second day because you
are having an extra lacking month. Okay. אמר ליה רב אדא בר
אבא לרבא. amar lei Rav Adda bar Abba l'Rava. So now רב
אדא בר אבא Rav Adda bar Abba says to רבא, Rava, אחרי
מניינא אתא לאשמועינן? acharei minyana ata l'ashmi'inan? What's רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir
coming to tell us, or אחרים acherim coming to tell us? That
on a normal calendar there's four days, we can do the math
too. So no, הא קמשמע לן, ha kamashma lan, he's telling us
actually quite a big thing, which is what Michael's saying, דלא בעינן
מצוה לקדש על פי ראייה, d'lo ba'inan mitzva l'kadesh al pi re'iya,
that we if we don't in the end of the day we
don't need witnesses. If there's no witnesses, we'll just do it ourselves.
And therefore, you're astounded, but how do you think our calendar works
nowadays? So therefore, but that was after... Okay, but isn't it better
to assume that we didn't innovate that, that that was always a
principle that in the absence of witnesses we can do it anyway?
But the גמרא Gemara. says in מסכת ראש השנה... Masechet Rosh Hashanah...
I understand, but the whole issue of that מסכת ראש השנה Masechet
Rosh Hashanah is dealing with the human factor of witnesses and the
reality, the astronomical reality, which is six. And what do you do
if the witnesses say one thing and we know the astronomical reality
to be another? So רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir is very focused on
the astronomical reality. He wants the calendar to always be really correct.
So he will always have sort of the, you
know, the override of the human problem.
And he will be prepared to do a קידוש kid... to set
up the months regardless of the witnesses. This is assuming the witnesses
come on day 29, right? So you know, if they
came, then we'd do it על פי al pi witnesses, but
if not, the בית דין Beis Din will say מקודש מקודש mekudash
mekudash anyway? Yeah, but I'm not sure we would do it the
first month because to some degree it's self-correcting, right? Because if one
month you did 30 and you should have done 29, then the
next month when you should have done 30, they'll see the new
moon on day 29. So a certain amount I imagine we would
allow because it will be self-correcting because they're always looking up at
the moon. But when it gets to a point where it's not...
where it's too late and we can't correct and we can't, then
we'll just do it ourselves and we'll make sure that the year
works out, you know, precisely. Yes. So they don't disregard the witnesses.
No, no, no, he's not
saying you completely ignore them, but it's saying that when you have
to, you just do it yourselves. You know, if you can't trust
somebody else, you gotta do it yourself. And yet... Well, that's Michael's
question, right?
Could it be that we set... what, if they have... how can
you just completely shut down בית דין Beis Din for business? Maybe
you could do that too. If we want it to be a
30-day month, then we're just not going to meet today. Congress is
in session, right? I mean, whatever, on recess. Or then we'll have
to have the filibuster to keep it not on recess, not a
filibuster, what was it they had? A 30-minute... anyway, fine. Okay, moving
on. So nobody got that reference. Okay, anyway, so now the גמרא
Gemara says like this. All right, so the גמרא Gemara says like
this. מתקיף לה רבינא. matkif lah Ravina. So רבינא Ravina said, wait
a minute, you can't say it's always four days. How do we
say four days?
Because I sort of simplified it.
I said assume a 29 and a half day lunar cycle. But
a lunar cycle is actually not 29 and a half days. A
lunar cycle is, if you look at רש״י, Rashi, he says like
this. 1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6,
7 lines from the bottom.
He says, איכא... ika... the previous line says from one מולד molad
to... but really the gap between two years is not four days,
but it's four days, איכא ארבעה ימים ושמונה שעות, ika arba yamim
v'shmoneh sha'ot, eight hours. I'm just... I'm in the middle of a
רש״י. Rashi. Eight lines... I'm not giving you the דיבור המתחיל. dibur
hamatchil. Seven lines from the bottom, line beginning with the word איכא.
ika. You see that? He says איכא, ika, so basically at the
end of a sentence, the real gap between one year and the
next is four days, which we did the math just now assuming
precisely 29 and a half. But it's not precisely 29 and a
half. Four days, eight hours, and תתע״ו, tat-ayin-vav, which is 876 חלקים.
chalakim. Now, like we just did קידוש החודש, Kiddush HaChodesh, what's a
חלק? chelek? A חלק chelek is one 1080th. The reason they... That
is because 1,080 is highly divisible by 2, by 3, by 4,
by 5. Anyway, but for our purposes it's easier to think of
it as point one percent. Just think of this one one-thousandth. Okay,
that's pretty close, right? Okay, so the real difference between years is
4 days, 8 hours, and this says 876, let's call it 900
one-thousandths, so basically it is... it is 90%... 90% of a minute.
Okay, so... that's what you have... or no, 90% of an hour.
Of a minute? Of an hour. Of a... he said a חלק
chelek is one one-thousand-eightieth of a what? Of a what? Right. I
think of an hour. Of an hour. Of an hour. Yeah, they
don't have minutes. Of an hour. Okay, fine. So this basically it's
off by then, by then it's off by 8 hours and... and
8.9 hours. Okay, that's the error. So now let's take a look.
So the גמרא Gemara says it's not always going to be a
4-day gap. Okay, so let's go back to the גמרא. The גמרא
says like this... okay. מתקיף לה רבינא ואיכא יומי דששא, Matkif lah
Ravina va'ika yomei deshasha, sometimes you'll get an extra day out of
the hours after 3 years, right? Every 3 years, 8 times 3
is 24. Every 3 years it's actually going to be another day
that it's going to be off. ויומא דתלתין שני, Ve'yoma detlasin shani,
every 30 years, because now look at the point nine, right? Right,
there was a... we were off by also a point nine hour.
Point nine times 30 is going to give you 27. So really
it wasn't point nine. Call it... call it point eight. Point eight,
right, times 30 is 24. So every 30 years that little... that
little piece of an hour is going to add up to an
extra day. So on the average every 3 years you're going to
have an extra day that that gap between... and every 30 years
yet another extra day. So the גמרא says, כיון דליתא בכל שתא,
keivan delaisa bechol shata, alright, that's true, but it's not every year.
לא קחשיב, lo kachashiv, we're not saying it. Although he says there's
always going to be 4 days from one ראש השנה Rosh Hashanah
to the next, that really means on the... you know, on a
normal year, but some years there actually will have to be 5
days from one ראש השנה Rosh Hashanah to the next. ואף שמואל
סבר לה כרב הונא, Ve'af Shmuel savar lah keRav Huna, and even
שמואל Shmuel holds like רב הונא, Rav Huna, דאמר שמואל, de'amar Shmuel,
שמואל Shmuel says, אין שנת לבנה פחותה משלש מאות וחמשים ושנים. ein
shenat levana pechuta mishlosh me'ot vachamishim ushnayim. What is a normal... how
much is a normal... how many days in a... in a leap
year... in a... in a lunar year? So let's do it easy.
Let's do 30 times 12 gets you 360, but really that we
added 6 extra days, right? Because 30 is assuming all the days
are מלא and we actually know half of them are חסר. So
360 minus 6 is 354. So 354 is perfect. If you allow
a 2-day variation on each side, it'll be between 352 and 356.
And that's what שמואל Shmuel says. אין שנת לבנה פחותה משלש מאות
וחמשים ושנים יום, ein shenat levana pechuta mishlosh me'ot vachamishim ushnayim yom,
no less than 352 days, ולא יתירה על שלש מאות וחמשים וששה
יום, velo yeteira al shlosh me'ot vachamishim veshisha yom, and no more
than 356 days. הא כיצד? ha keitzad? How do you get that?
שנים מלאים, shnayim mele'im, if you have 2 extra full months, ששה,
shisha, then that gets you 356. שנים חסרים, shnayim chaseirim, if you
have 2 extra lacking months, then שנים, shnayim, that gets it to
be 352. אחד מלא ואחד חסר, echad malei ve'echad chaseir, if you
have your normal variation, full and lacking, then ארבע, arba, 354. Of
course you could have, you know, you could have also done the
5 and the 3. Anyway. מיתיבי, meitivei, they object. הריני נזיר, hareini
nazir, if somebody takes a vow that's in a נזירות nezirus and
says, I am a נזיר כימות החמה, nazir kiyemot hachama, according to
the number of days of a lunar... of a solar year. מונה
נזירות כשלש מאות וששים וחמשה ימים, moneh nezirus kishlosh me'ot veshishim vachamisha
yamim, so his נזירות nezirus is of 365 days, כמנין ימות החמה,
keminyan yemot hachama, like a... like a lunar year... like a solar
year. If he says כימות הלבנה, kiyemot halevana, I'm a נזיר... nazir...
he's talking about leap years? Right. So you do by the... by
the normal. If you say like a lunar year, מונה נזירות כשלש
מאות וחמשים וארבעה ימים, moneh nezirus kishlosh me'ot vachamishim ve'arba'a yamim, 354,
כמנין ימות הלבנה, keminyan yemot halevana, like a lunar year. ואי איתא,
ve'im ita, and if it's true that it really varies between 352
and 356, לימני תשעה וששה, limnei tish'a veshisha, maybe he should be
safe and do 356, right? Because a lunar year could be as
much as 356. Let's be... let's be safe. So the גמרא says,
בנדרים הלך אחר לשון בני אדם, binedarim halach achar leshon benei adam,
by vows you go by the vernacular. וברוב שנים, uverov shanim, and
you go by most years. Most people, they refer to a standard
year as 354. ואף רב סבר לה כרב הונא, ve'af Rav savar
lah keRav Huna, even רב Rav holds like רב הונא, Rav Huna,
that it can be 8 full months. דתניא, detanya, מעשה ועשה רבי,
ma'aseh ve'asa Rebbi, I'm sorry, רבי, Rebbi, רבי Rebbi holds like רב
הונא. Rav Huna. מעשה ועשה רבי, ma'aseh ve'asa Rebbi, obviously it didn't
say כרב הונא keRav Huna because רבי Rebbi was a little bit
before רב הונא. Rav Huna. מעשה ועשה רבי תשעה חסרים. ma'aseh ve'asa
Rebbi tish'a chaseirim. He made 9 lacking months. So here actually he
var... he went beyond the limits, but we're going to see it
was to correct the calendar. ונראה חודש בזמנו, venira chodesh bizmano, but
look at that, he made too many lacking months and actually ראש
השנה Rosh Hashanah fell out on the... exactly when the moon appeared.
והיה רבי תמיה, vehaya Rebbi tameha, that how did... how did that
happen? דאמר עשינו תשעה... de'amar asinu tish'a... We made nine lacking months
and it fell out that Rosh Hashanah was the right time. So
you wonder why was he doing nine lacking months, but anyway, so
אמר לפניו Amar lefanav רבי שמעון בר רבי, Rabbi Shimon bar Rabbi,
so his son said to him, שמא שנה מעוברת היתה, shema shana
me'uberet hayta, maybe last year was an עיבור eiber year? Okay, the
עיבור eiber I know, like it's like you know where were they
and how did they let nine months happen? Anyway, the עיבור שנה
ל', eiber shana lamed, and we made last year a thirty day
month, okay, I'm sorry, or this year, excuse me, not last year,
this year we made as a, we added a thirty day month,
which to get, which would have pushed us forward, right, a half
a day, if you remember that discussion, right, if you make it
thirty it represents twenty-nine and a half, it pushes you forward half
a day. ואשתקד, Ve'ishtakad, and last year, עשינו שנים מלאים, asinu shenayim
mele'im, we did the limit the other way, we did two extra
full months. So last year we did two extra full months, so
we were ahead two days. This year we had a leap year
which we made thirty days, which put us ahead another half a
day. So we were off, but we were two and a half
days ahead. So therefore, דא תלתא לבהדי תלתא, da telasa levahadei telasa,
so now he had three extra חסרים, chaseirim, it pulled us back
to exactly where we needed to be, וקם ליה בדוכתא, vekam lei
beduchta, and that put us back into place. So אמר ליה, amar
lei, נר ישראל, ner Yisrael, כן היה, kein haya, oh you, that's
exactly the way it was. Of course you wonder like how the
whole thing happened and he didn't know it happened, but what it
shows you is that he allowed last year to have two extra
days and therefore you see that you can vary between having two,
you know, two months that are extra, months that are חסר and
two extra months that are מלא. And with that, tomorrow's going to
be a lot easier. See you tomorrow.